A Guide to the Correspondence of T.S. Eliot with the League of Dramatists
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Correspondence of T.S. Eliot with the League of Dramatists
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6247-v
The collection consists of 68 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from Stuart Lutz, 2008 May 29.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of about sixty letters from T.S. Eliot, almost exclusively through Valerie Fletcher and other secretaries, to Ann Munro-Kerr and the League of Dramatists, concerning publishing rights, translations and performances. There are three letters signed by Eliot and sent to members of the League of Dramatists and one signed letter sent to Rudolfo Usigli (1905-1979), a Mexican playwright. There are also six printed items and news clippings.
All of T.S. Eliot's letters are foldered singly and occur first on the list; next is the folder of correspondence from The League of Dramatists to Eliot; followed last by the folders of letters written by his secretaries to the League on his behalf, including those of his future wife, Valerie Fletcher. The letters written by the secretaries are in chronological order.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - 1949 September 16 T.S. Eliot to Miss M.E. Barber, The League of Dramatists, informing her that he cannot join her on October 21, as he will be away that weekend, TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:1)
  - 1950 Aug 31 T.S. Eliot to Senor Rodolfo Usigli (1905-1979), Mexican playwright, concerning his request to translate The Cocktail Party which he is unable to give because Faber and Faber had already authorized a translation which was to be published by Emece in Buenos Aires in Spanish. He does write that he could use his own translation for production in Mexico, after he has secured the performance rights from the League of Dramatists in London, TL, 1 page (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1951 November 22 T.S. Eliot to Miss Anne Munro-Kerr, The League of Dramatists, asks them to draw up a contract for a repertory engagement for a play which has already had its first run, with Monsieur Jean Vilar, who was responsible for the production of Murder in the Cathedral in Paris in 1945, but leave the attempts to arrange a French production of The Cocktail Party to Monsieur Fluchere, TLS, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1963 November 27 T.S. Eliot to Miss Anne Munro-Kerr, responding to a letter from Signor Fulvio Fo, Eliot does not object to licensing a new Italian translation of an unidentified work for use in the theatre, since "it appears to be required by a distinguished actor, who, as they say, understands the play." TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 1950-1960 The League of Dramatists, London, to T.S. Eliot, Faber and Faber, London, thanks Eliot for the copy of the agreement between him and Mr. G.M. Hoellering for the film of Murder in the Cathedral and informs him of the receipt of the dossier from Ashley Dukes (March 30, 1950); lists the details for all the foreign inquiries that they have received for The Confidential Clerk, including France, Germany, Holland, Italy, Scandinavia, and Spain (October 2, 1953); returns the letter from the People's Theatre at Newcastle, an amateur company who wanted to perform a part of The Confidential Clerk before it was generally released to amateurs, and suggests that Eliot suggest they choose some other play for use in their pageant-history of English Drama; American terms of the renewal of copyright were also discussed (November 5, 1954); and thanks Miss Angela Miles for her letter about the reduced royalties for Murder in the Cathedral (May 25, 1960), 5 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1945 Secretary to T.S. Eliot, L. Melton, to the League of British Dramatists, thanks Miss Barber for enclosing membership forms for the League and asks what is mean by "the levy prescribed should a member not employ the League for collecting his performance fees" (June 29, 1945); and returns the membership form with payment by a bankers order (August 14, 1945), 2 items (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1950-1954 Secretary to T.S. Eliot, Valerie Fletcher, to the League of Dramatists, Eliot gives the Tavistock Repertory Company permission to perform an excerpt from The Family Reunion (September 18, 1950); acknowledges that Senor Olivers is the authorized translator of The Cocktail Party and the publisher as Emece of Buenos Aires (November 8 and December 21, 1950); Eliot desires to continue his contracts with Suhrkamp Verlag and thinks it best to have two separate contracts for each play in the future, one for book publication and the other for production rights (January 10 and 19, 1951); thanks them for the press-cuttings of the Italian production of The Cocktail Party, as Eliot was interested in the criticisms (January 17, 1951); discusses the offer by Senor Usigli concerning "Spanish language production" (January 19, 1951); permission for some Japanese students to give a limited number of performances of The Cocktail Party without any fee (June 5, 1951); encloses three signed copies of The Cocktail Party with the authorization form for Mexican copyright and agrees that the new contracts with Suhrkamp Verlag be extended to cover productions in Austria and Switzerland concerning Murder in the Cathedral and The Family Reunion (June 15, 1951); permits three performances of Murder in the Cathedral by the Musiske Studenter for a nominal fee (October 1, 1951); inquires about the details of his receipts from the publisher Bompiani and Italian productions (October 25, 1951); asks that they grant Senor Francisco Carreres of Valencia the performing rights of Murder in the Cathedral under a translation contract (December 20, 1951); Eliot feels that the first option on the rights of his next play should be given to Bonniers of Stockholm (July 8, 1952); Eliot not enthusiastic about a cheap American acting edition of The Cocktail Party (July 14, 1952); refers to the Dutch contract for Murder in the Cathedral and forwards criticism of the current translation from Holland (October 7, 1952); Eliot agrees "that 'Guardian Angels' is too precise and limiting a term. He purposely kept a certain ambiguity in the play, and therefore feels that Mr. Leitao ought to be asked to find a more indefinite and less theological term than 'Guardian Angels." (December 8, 1952); instructs them to not renew Pere Boon's license for Murder in the Cathedral but grant them to the other unidentified man (January 28, 1953); discusses the details of the Spanish contract (November 27, 1953); Eliot voices no objections to a single performance of the translation of Murder in the Cathedral by Mr. Ley's student as long as it doesn't prejudice the use of other translations (April 22, 1954); writes concerning his agreement with Monsieur Morazzani (August 13, 1954); and discusses several letters she sent to The League of Dramatists from the Newcastle People's Theatre and the Taw & Torridge Festival Society (November 4, 1954). (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1958-1960 Secretary to T.S. Eliot, Ann Macfadyen, to the League of Dramatists, encloses a letter from Mr. Kellner of Coe College (November 11, 1958); another from the Yale Drama School where he suggests a nominal fee (November 14, 1958); accepts the amount of payment suggested from the Educational Television and Radio Center, Ann Arbor for the right to three television showings of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation's production of The Family Reunion (May 27, 1959); thanks for letting him see the photographs and press cuttings from the Italian production of The Elder Statesman (January 7, 1960); forwards a letter from Martin Browne who was told by Eliot to contact The League of Dramatists (March 8, 1960), 6 items (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1960-1961 July Secretary to T.S. Eliot, Angela Miles, to the League of Dramatists, sends an enclosed letter from Leonard Lambert agreeing to reduction in fees for the performance of Murder in the Cathedral but "hopes that Murder in the Cathedral will not become so popular for charitable performances that it will cease to bring in anything to the author or to the League of Dramatists (May 18 and 24, 1960); asks them to deal with a request from Miss Julia Baker of Mexico about The Cocktail Party (September 14, 1960); and passes on a dubious request from Safford Chamberlain (November 15, 1960), 7 items (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1961 September-1962 July Secretary to T.S. Eliot, Jane Mosley, to the League of Dramatists, thanks them for the extract of the letter from Charles Adams which she will forward to Eliot (September 7 and November 15, 1961); and sends questions about a request from Mr. Sackler of Philips Records, Ltd. about the rights of "Sweeney Agonistes" being available for making a gramophone recording (October 17, 1961), 4 items (Box-folder 1:10)
  - 1962 December-1963 Secretary to T.S. Eliot, Pamela Barker, to the League of Dramatists, returns signed agreements from Eliot concerning a possible production of The Elder Statesman in Turkey for 1963 (December 13, 1962); encloses an agreement with Teatr Dramatyczny to produce The Family Reunion (December 28, 1962); encloses a copy of a letter from Signor F. de A. Carreres for their opinion of his request (March 1 and May 13, 1963); Eliot returns from Bermuda today and she will bring the correspondence about the production of Murder in the Cathedral to his attention (May 2 and 13, 1963); Eliot does not give his permission for Murder in the Cathedral to be produced as a puppet show in Great Britain or for Mrs. Masefield's proposes cuts for the play (May 27, 1963); refers a letter from Professor Vincenzo Arangio-Ruiz (May 28, 1963); and sends a press cutting for them to check on whether permission was sought to produce Sweeney Agonistes (July 24, 1963), 8 items (Box-folder 1:11)
  - 1951-1963 Printed and News clippings, includes: an invitation to an exhibition of sets, properties and costumes used in the production of the film version of Murder in the Cathedral; a press release for Eliot's book On Poetry and Poets; a news clipping about Valerie Fletcher Eliot (September 25, 1958); and a news clipping about the production of Sweeney Agonistes (July [5?], 1963), 6 items (Box-folder 1:12)